A Guide to the Laurance S. Rockefeller papers, Speech Files, RG 5 FA434
Rockefeller Archive Center
Laurance S. Rockefeller papers, Speech Files, RG 5
1941-2004
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
FA434
14.25 Cubic Feet 37 document boxes and one half-document box.
Biographical/Historical note
Laurance Spelman Rockefeller was born on May 26, 1910, in New York City, the fourth of the six children of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He attended Lincoln School, a progressive coeducational preparatory school connected with Teachers College of Columbia University in New York City, before entering Princeton in 1928. A philosophy major, he graduated from Princeton in 1932 with a B.A. degree in philosophy and went on to two years of graduate study at Harvard Law School.
On August 15, 1934, Laurance Rockefeller married Mary French in the Congregational Church in Woodstock, Vermont. Together they raised three daughters and a son.
During World War II, Laurance Rockefeller served in the Navy (1942-1945), attaining the rank of lieutenant commander.
Laurance Rockefeller pursued a number of successful careers during his lifetime. He was a pioneer in the field of venture capital. He was a leading and influential figure for three decades in the American conservation movement. He led the development of one of the world's foremost cancer care and research facilities, and was both a benefactor and advisor to major educational institutions. And, with great foresight, he combined his personal vision for conservation, recreation and the spiritual needs of individuals to develop internationally acclaimed environmentally-oriented resorts. His many accomplishments have been recognized both nationally and internationally.
In 1935, he began working in the family office in Rockefeller Center. His first duties were to develop his knowledge and understanding of Rockefeller philanthropic activities, conservation projects and business interests, through both study and playing a modest role in their operation. Simultaneously, he developed his own special interest, blending business acumen with the talents of a "gadgeteer," a label he once pinned on himself.
He became well known as an investor of risk capital in young enterprises whose future was based primarily on scientific and technological developments. Over the years his investment interests included the fields of aviation, aerospace, electronics, high temperature physics, composite materials, optics, lasers, data processing, thermionics, instrumentation and nuclear power. Beginning in August 1969, his venture capital investments in these areas were made through a venture capital group, Venrock, formed by members of the Rockefeller family.
In a different area of venture capital, he developed outstanding environmentally oriented resort hotels in Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Hawaii and Vermont, serving as chairman of Rockresorts, Inc., a resort management company which he founded and chaired.
Conservation of the environment and recreational development constituted much of Laurance Rockefeller's philanthropy and public service. His introduction to public service came in 1939 when Governor Herbert H. Lehman of New York appointed him to the Palisades Interstate Park Commission (PIPC). He was president of the PIPC from 1970 to 1977 and continued as a commissioner until his resignation in December 1978. He was an advisor to Presidents Eisenhower, Kennedy, Johnson, Nixon and Ford on matters of environmental conservation and outdoor recreation, and he worked on federal commissions set up to help develop national conservation and environmental policies and programs. In 1958, President Dwight D. Eisenhower appointed him chairman of the Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission (ORRRC), which charted ways of meeting the nation's outdoor recreation needs through the year 2000. He was a special emissary for President Lyndon Johnson in the effort that led to creation of the National Redwoods Park in California, and he served as chairman of President Nixon's Citizens' Advisory Committee on Environmental Quality, successor to a similar group which he headed under President Johnson. He played a pivotal role in the creation and development of several national parks including Grand Teton National Park in Wyoming, Virgin Islands National Park on the island of St. John and Marsh, Billings, Rockefeller National Historical Park in Vermont.
He served as a leader of several important nonprofit and philanthropic organizations. He was president and later chairman of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1958-1980) and was a trustee of the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation (1960-1982). His first association with Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center in New York City was in 1947; he also served as chairman (1960-1982), overseeing an expansion and modernization of its operations. He was a longtime trustee of the New York Zoological Society (1935-1986) and served as its president (1969-1971) and chairman (1971-1985).
Laurance Rockefeller received many honors for his efforts on behalf of the environment and cancer research and treatment. Among them are the Alfred P. Sloan, Jr. Memorial Award from the American Cancer Society (1969), the Medal of Freedom (1969), Commander (Honorary) of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire (1971), the Woodrow Wilson Award from Princeton University (1991), the Congressional Gold Medal (1991), the Chairman's Award from the National Geographic Society (1995), the Theodore Roosevelt National Park Medal of Honor (1995), and the Lady Bird Johnson Conservation Award for Lifetime Achievement (1997). In 2003, he became the first person to be made an honorary citizen of the British Virgin Islands in recognition of his many contributions to the area. In December 1959 he received the National Institute of Social Sciences' Gold Medal for distinguished services to humanity, an award previously bestowed upon his grandfather and father. This was the first time in the Institute's history that three generations of a family had been so honored. The citation to Laurance Rockefeller proclaimed him as a "creative organizer of ventures into new fields of human endeavor for the growing aspirations of mankind; [and a] leader in the conservation of natural resources and in the development of the medical and social sciences for the welfare of the individual." In 1967, the National Institute awarded Gold Medals to all five Rockefeller brothers in recognition of their individual and collective services to humanity.
Laurance Rockefeller died on July 11, 2004 at his home in Manhattan.
Prepared by Rockefeller Family and Associates, June 1982, and 2004.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted. Access is subject to the restrictions specified in the original deed of gift of November 13, 1986, and in the subsequent 2009 deed of gift by LSR's executors.
Material in the Rockefeller family collections which provides the names, correspondence or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net worth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Laurance S. Rockefeller papers include:
FA433 Laurance S. Rockefeller papers, Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, RG 2
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: speeches and related materials.
- Speech Files, 1941-2004; 5; 38 document box(es)
  Arrangement note
  The speech files are arranged chronologically by the date of the speech.
  Related Archival Materials note
  Speech-related materials are also found in files labeled "Addresses," included in the Personal Papers series of other record groups of the Laurance S. Rockefeller papers.
  Scope and Contents note
  Laurance S. Rockefeller's speeches were assembled into a consolidated file in late 1985-1986 by his associate George Taylor and Rockefeller family archivist Joseph M. Ernst. The aim was to create a master file that would be available for ready reference and searchable by date, institution, occasion, or subject. The family office integrated later speeches into this series. In some cases, speech files have been added from other accessions of LSR's papers.
  - Speech File and Workbook, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This file contains background materials on outdoor recreation and natural beauty. The first part of the file consists of sections labeled Watts Branch, Youth Conference, Philanthropy in Texas, Mrs. Humphrey, LBJ Book, Advisory Committee, Botanical Gardens, Department of Natural Resources, and Hudson River. These materials, all of which date from 1966, appear to provide background information for LSR meetings with Lady Bird Johnson.
    The second part of the file, entitled Speech Workbook, is a compilation, circa 1963-1965, of key points relating to outdoor recreation. It is divided into the following sections: The Need, Creative Leisure, The ORRRC (Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission) Study, Classification System, Bureau of Outdoor Recreation, Multiple Use, Private Land, New Devices, Political Action, Role of State and Local Governments, Training, and Selected Quotations.
  - Compilation of Speech Files - Correspondence, 1958-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1941
    - Air Youth of America, 1941 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Air Youth of America, 1941 April 24 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1946-1950
    - Dean Cornwell Mural, Rockefeller Center, 1946 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Comments made upon acceptance of mural from Captain Rickenbacker and Eastern Air Lines.
    - New York City Airport Authority, 1947 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Statement made before the New York City Board of Estimate on behalf of the New York City Airport Authority.
    - Jackson Hole Wildlife Park Opening Ceremonies, 1948 July 19 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Saunders Memorial Fountain, Palisades Interstate Park, 1948 October 7 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Dedication of Nell Baker Saunders Memorial Fountain; LSR representing Palisades Interstate Park Commission.
    - Children's Pavilion Dedication, Memorial Cancer Center, 1950 December 20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1951-1954
    - The Society of Memorial Cancer Center, 1951 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Overview of past year's accomplishments and looking to the future.
    - Memorial Hospital Dinner, 1951 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Dinner to welcome new members of resident staff.
    - Tower Clinic Dedication, Memorial Cancer Center, 1951 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Women's National Republican Club, 1951 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Memorial Cancer Center, Alice Hill Chittenden Treatment Room, Clinic Building.
    - Dinner in Honor of Mr. Pierre Wigny, 1952 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Belgian Congo.
    - Unveiling of Kettering Portrait, Sloan-Kettering Institute, 1953 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Dedication of Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Hall, Spelman College, 1953 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Dedication of Recovery Ward, Strang Prevention Clinic, 1954 January 5 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Unveiling of Dr. L'Esperance's portrait.
    - Assurance Fund Dinner, Memorial Cancer Center, 1954 March 2 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Address to Volunteers, Memorial Cancer Center, 1954 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Speech entitled "Volunteer Recognition," given at Annual Meeting of The Society of Memorial Cancer Center.
    - Groundbreaking Ceremony, New York Zoological Society, New Aquarium, 1954 Otober 24 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Virgin Islands National Park, Press Release, 1954 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Announcement of plan to offer land on St. John for the establishment of a national park.
  - 1955-1956
    - Jackson Lake Lodge Dedication, Jackson Hole Preserve, Inc., 1955 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Tenth Anniversary Party, Sloan-Kettering Institute, 1955 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Fall Appeal Meeting, Memorial Cancer Center, 1955 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Group Affiliates, Citation Meeting, Memorial Center, 1955 November 22 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Sloan Fellows, Venture Capital Investment, 1955 December (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Title: Venture capital investment and its point of similarity to effective giving or philanthropy.
    - New York Zoological Society Annual Meeting, 1956 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Kerbs Memorial Hall, Memorial Cancer Center, 1956 April 9 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Unveiling of portraits of Edward A. and Alice H. Kerbs.
    - Fall Appeal Luncheon, Memorial Cancer Center, 1956 January 30 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Founders Day Exercises, Spelman College 25th Anniversary, 1956 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - State Council of Parks Meeting, Palisades Interstate Park Commission, 1956 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Annual Appeal Luncheon, Memorial Center, 1956 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Group Affiliates, Citation Meeting, Memorial Center, 1956 October 31 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Virgin Islands National Park Dedication, 1956 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - 1957-1958
    - Opening of Link, Palisades Interstate Parkway, 1957 January 19 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Eighth Annual Arboretum Day, Garden Club of New Jersey, 1957 May 8 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Topic: Palisades Interstate Park.
    - National Park Service Development Conference, 1957 September 17 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      Title of address: "People and Parks: National, State and Community." Conference held at Jackson Lake Lodge.
    - Dedication of Sunday School Building, Union Church of Pocantico Hills, 1957 September 29 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - New York Times Youth Forum, "Are We Wasting Our Natural Resources?", 1957 November 17 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Memorial Center Thrift Shop Annual Luncheon, 1958 Fall (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Buckley School Commencement, 1958 June 5 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Annual Appeal Committee, Opening Meeting, Memorial Center, 1958 October 14 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Dorado Beach Hotel Opening, 1958 December 2 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - 1959
    - North American Wildlife Conference, 1959 March 4 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      Title of address: "Meeting Future Recreational Needs"; LSR speaking as Chairman of National Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission.
    - Izaak Walton League of America 37th Annual Convention, 1959 April 22 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      Title of address: "The Citizen's Opportunity and the Outdoor Recreation Resources Review"; LSR speaking as Chairman of National Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission.
    - Clement Cleveland Award, New York City Cancer Committee, 1959 May 6 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - House of Representatives Committee on Appropriations, Special Subcommittee on Deficiencies, Report on ORRRC, 1959 June 18 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission.
    - Rockefeller Center Time and Life Building, Cornerstone, 1959 June 23 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Senate Committee on Appropriations, Subcommittee on Interior and Related Agencies, Report on ORRRC, 1959 July 21 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - New York Times Article: "People and Parks", 1959 July 31 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Memorial Service for Dr. C. P. Rhoads, Memorial Center, 1959 September 22 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Annual Appeal Committee, Opening Meeting, Memorial Center, 1959 September 30 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - American Forestry Association 84th Annual Meeting, 1959 October 13 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      Theme of meeting: "Resources and People - A Challenge of Co-existence"; LSR speaking as Chairman of Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission.
    - Rockefeller Center, Tree Lighting Ceremony, 1959 December 10 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - National Institute of Social Sciences, Presentation of Gold Medal, 1959 December 15 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - 1960
    - House of Representatives Committee on Appropriations, Subcommittee on the Department of the Interior and Related Agencies, Report on ORRRC, 1960 January 21 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Senate Committee on Appropriations, Subcommittee on the Interior and Related Agencies, Report on ORRRC, 1960 February 11 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Rockefeller Center, American Metal Climax Building, Unveiling of Granite Stones, 1960 March 2 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - 75th Anniversary Dinner, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 1960 April 20 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - National Governors Conference, Report on ORRRC, 1960 June (Box 2, Folder 60)
      Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission; Title of address: ""Some Problems in Providing Outdoor Recreation Facilities as Seen by the States".
    - Connecticut College, Commencement Address, 1960 June 12 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Westinghouse Program, Introduction to "The Power of the Democratic Idea", 1960 September 12 (Box 3, Folder 62)
      LSR's introduction to last of six reports from a Rockefeller Brothers Fund Special Studies Project.
    - Annual Appeal Committee, First Meeting, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 1960 September 9 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Forty-Second National Recreation Congress, ORRRC, 1960 September 25 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Radio and Television Executive Society "Newsmaker Luncheon", 1960 October 26 (Box 3, Folder 65)
      LSR speaking as Chairman of Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission.
    - Rockefeller Center, Tree Lighting Ceremony, 1960 December 12 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Colonial Williamsburg, Background, 1960 December 12 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - 1961
    - House of Representatives, Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs, ORRRC, 1961 January 13 (Box 3, Folder 68)
      Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission; LSR reporting as Chairman.
    - Brick Church Women's Association, "Outdoor Recreation - Its Need and Opportunity", 1961 January 17 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - House of Representatives Committee on Appropriations, Subcommittee on the Department of the Interior and Related Agencies, ORRRC, 1961 March 8 (Box 3, Folder 70)
      Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission; LSR statement regarding request for funds.
    - Public Affairs Committee Panel Discussion, "Open Space and the Creative Use of Leisure Time", 1961 March 24 (Box 3, Folder 71)
      Panel Discussion on the Use of Leisure, 25th Anniversary Conference, "The Years of Challenge," Public Affairs Committee, Hotel Biltmore, New York.
    - State University College of Forestry, Syracuse University, 50th Anniversary Celebration Program, "Challenges in the Use of Forest Resources", 1961 April 13 (Box 3, Folder 72)
      LSR, speaking as Chairman of Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission, on "Future Demand for Recreation and Space."
    - Clement Cleveland Award to Mrs. Edward P. Hutton, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 1961 May 17 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - State Council of Parks Meeting, 1961 May 19 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - National Conference of Christians and Jews, Brotherhood Award Luncheon Honoring Michael Daroff, 1961 June 12 (Box 3, Folder 75)
      Full title: Brotherhood Award Luncheon of the Men's Wear Division.
    - Unveiling of Plaque in Memory of George W. Perkins, Palisades Interstate Park Commission, 1961 October 21 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - The Academy of Religion and Mental Health, First Annual Dinner, "The Divinity and Naturalness of Man", 1961 October 26 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Rockefeller Center, Tree Lighting Ceremony, 1961 December 7 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - 1962
    - Statement on Breezy Point Park Proposals; and Statement Before the House Interior and Insular Affairs Committee, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 79)
      Statement on Breezy Point Park Proposals, 1963 July 23; Statement on H.R. 1762, H.R. 1763 and H.R. 3541 before the House Interior and Insular Affairs Committee, 1963 February 12.
    - Anderson-Bartlett Bill Amending New York State Constitution, State Council of Parks, 1962 March 2 (Box 3, Folder 80)
      LSR statement regarding Anderson-Bartlett Bill, an amendment creating a new Section 1, Article 14 of the Constitution, classifying Forest Preserve into three major categories.
    - University of Michigan, School of Natural Resources, 1962 April 20 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Senate Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs, Statement Urging Passage of S. 3117, ORRRC, 1962 May 10 (Box 3, Folder 82)
      Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission; Statement in favor of S. 3117 creating a Bureau of Outdoor Recreation; folder contains prior speeches as background (1958-1962).
    - White House Conference on Conservation, 1962 May 24 (Box 4, Folder 83)
      Includes introductions of Secretary Udall and Administrator Weaver.
    - Rockefeller Center, 20-Year Dinner, "Rockefeller Center, Thirty Years Young", 1962 June 6 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Phillips Exeter Academy, Cum Laude Society Lunch, 1962 June 10 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Opening of Lake Welch Beach, Harriman State Park, Palisades Interstate Park Commission, 1962 June 15 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Izaak Walton League of America, "Where Do We Go From Here?" Report on ORRRC, 1962 June 22 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - House of Representatives Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs, Subcommittee on National Parks, H.R. 11165, 1962 July 10 (Box 4, Folder 88)
      LSR statement urging passage of H.R. 11165 and related bills "vital to the effective functioning of the new Bureau of Outdoor Recreation".
    - Dedication of JDR Jr. Memorial Plaque, Rockefeller Center, 1962 July 16 (Box 4, Folder 89)
      Plaque containing JDR Jr.'s Credo.
    - Sloan House Dedication, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 1962 September 11 (Box 4, Folder 90)
      In memory of Irene Jackson Sloan.
  - 1963
    - State Council of Parks, Remarks Accepting Chairmanship, 1963 January 17 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission, Statement on Formation of Citizens Committee for ORRRC Report, 1963 February 5 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Senate Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs, Statement on S. 20, 1963 February 5 (Box 4, Folder 93)
      Bill concerns Bureau of Outdoor Recreation.
    - Second Urban County Congress, National Association of Counties, 1963 February 7 (Box 4, Folder 94)
      LSR topic: "Recreation for Metropolitan America."
    - House of Representatives Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs, Statement on H.R. 1762, H.R. 1763 and H.R. 3541, 1963 February 12 (Box 4, Folder 95)
      LSR statement urging "support of legislation to give the Bureau of Outdoor Recreation a Congressional mandate to carry out the functions which the [Outdoor Recreation Resources Review] Commission recommended."
    - Eighth Annual AFL-CIO National Conference on Community Services, Theme: The Shorter Work Week and the Constructive Use of Free Time", 1963 April 4 (Box 4, Folder 96)
      LSR remarks entitled "Free Time and Outdoor Recreation."
    - National Council of State Garden Clubs, "Molding Our Environment for Modern Living", 1963 April 15 (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - The Community Blood Council of Greater New York, Emergency Meeting, 1963 May 2 (Box 4, Folder 98)
      Concerning the Blood Council's Blood Center (and Research Institute).
    - Dedication of Dr. Connie Guion Building, New York Hospital-Cornell Medical Center, 1963 May 8 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Palisades Interstate Park Commission Meeting, Report on Recent Legislation, 1963 May 15 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - House of Representatives Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs, Subcommittee on National Parks, Statement on Land and Water Conservation Fund Bill, 1963 May 27 (Box 4, Folder 101)